<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Python | DoubleMap Engineering]]></title>
  <link href="http://doublemap.github.io/blog/categories/python/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://doublemap.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-28T10:45:32-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://doublemap.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[The DoubleMap team]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Everyone Panic! Almost Free Downtime Phone Alerts]]></title>
    <link href="http://doublemap.github.io/blog/2014/05/29/everyone-panic/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-29T11:24:46-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://doublemap.github.io/blog/2014/05/29/everyone-panic</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://github.com/doublemap/everyonepanic">Uptime Robot (free) + App Engine (free) + Twilio (cheap) = almost free
downtime alerts!</a></p>

<ol>
<li>Uptime Robot notices that your website is not responding.</li>
<li>Everyone Panic! checks Uptime Robot and sees that something is down.</li>
<li>You get a call through Twilio telling you to panic.</li>
<li>You get another call 15 minutes later because you still haven&rsquo;t fixed the
problem.</li>
</ol>


<p>Sure, it&rsquo;s easy to get emailed when your website goes down, but real
honest-to-goodness phone calls have an immediacy that&rsquo;s hard to beat.</p>

<p>Since our GPS bus-tracking system is used at all hours of the day, early on we
introduced automated monitoring. But when everyone is asleep, emails and text
messages go unnoticed until the morning and it sucks to not know where your
bus is at 1am.</p>

<p>We quickly whipped an app together using Python to tie
Uptime Robot and Twilio together. If one of the items in Uptime Robot goes
down then the Python app will ask Twilio to call us. We made it, put it on App
Engine, and haven&rsquo;t touched it since. With zero maintenance, it dutifully
watches Uptime Robot for any websites that are down.</p>

<p>Literally, there have been zero commits to the original repo since the first
day. Now I&rsquo;ve taken the code, cleaned it up, and
<a href="https://github.com/doublemap/everyonepanic">put it up on GitHub</a>.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s not entirely free &ndash; you&rsquo;ll need to pay Twilio for voice calls, but the
price is $0.02 per call and it&rsquo;s hard to think of a situation where knowing
your website is down isn&rsquo;t worth two cents. And, of course, you should keep
your Twilio account balance in the black.</p>

<p>But for the hobbyist who doesn&rsquo;t mind trying out a new app, this is a really
simple way to have your phone ring when Hacker News tramples your latest pet
project.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/doublemap/everyonepanic">Everyone Panic! on GitHub</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
